imagine a battlefield of the future
one where this one megawatt laser Turret exists
it fires green beams of light
from its one meter wide Turret
powered by a one hundred kilowatt hour battery
that's enough for six minutes of continuous firing
the whole weapon fits inside a standard shipping
container and it can be carried by most heavy trucks
if a generator can be hooked to the truck's
own five hundred horsepower engine
then the battery can be recharged in about sixteen minutes
this laser can focus its beam onto a five centimeter
wide spot at a distance of fifty kilometers  there
the intensity will be fifty
kilowatts per square centimeter
now introduce some targets
a nearby air defense radar picks up a
squad of four jet aircraft flying low
it transmits the tracking information to the laser
normally the pilots have forty to sixty seconds from hearing
the Radar warning signal to release their payload and duck
down behind the horizon breaking the targeting lock
but lasers travel at light speed
the Beam weapon turns the first plane into a
fireball within two hundred milliseconds of firing
the whole engagement is over within four seconds
this technology will change how wars are fought
and they are already being
deployed in live war zones today
how do they work
and how will warfare change
let's investigate the impending era of laser weapons
militarys around the world are spending millions of dollars
each year developing laser weapons and mounting them on
trucks and ships or integrating them into air defenses
what's got them so invested in this technology
the lasers you probably know about are very weak
handheld laser pointers have beam
powers measured in milliwatts
while the bright beams of a laser
show manage a few tens of Watts
these are far less powerful than even a light bulb
but it's very concentrated light
so it will damage camera sensors or injure your eyes
military lasers like range finders or target
designators are not much more powerful than that
they only need the beam to bounce off a surface
and remain visible across a large distance
a laser weapon tries instead to blow it up by
melting metals and exploding fuel tanks
it does this by focusing tens of thousands of
Watts onto a small point on the target
as if it was being heated by a dozen blow torches
the most powerful of these laser
weapons wields three hundred kilowatts
which is equivalent to delivering a stick
of tnt to a target every three seconds
that's what we have today
what military planners dream of is a
laser with a megawatt of power
with a few extra features
it would produce green wavelength light instead
of invisible infrared and be focused by a large
one meter diameter mirror in a turret
we will explain how it works
but first let's see what it can do
drones wouldn't last more than a
blink of an eye under its beam
they'd be destroyed as fast as
the turret can switch targets
missiles don't fare much better
as long as the laser weapon is given good
tracking data by an air defense radar
it can eliminate entire waves of over a
hundred missiles before they can reach it
all without ever having to reload
satellites sailing overhead are not safe either
low orbit satellites could have
holes melted in their solar panels
and higher altitude ones could get their cameras burnt out
but lasers are not the ultimate weapon
they're still dependent on radars
pointing out their targets
can only shoot at things within their line of sight
and few platforms today can handle the
electric consumption they need
properly armored vehicles like
tanks can shrug off their beams
and lasers can do nothing against targets
behind hills or beyond the horizon
yes  the advantages they do have are so great
they cannot be ignored  so
the real question is why aren't
laser weapons everywhere already
lasers have been around for over six decades
and it's hard to imagine a world without them today
in nineteen sixty
Gordon Gould at the Hughes research lab in California
managed to produce a Beam of deep red coherent light
he did it by taking a Ruby Crystal and pumping a
burst of energy into it using Flash lamps
chromium atoms in the crystal absorb the light energy
entering an excited state
which they shed as photons of a specific red wavelength
by placing the Ruby inside a tube with mirrors at both ends
one reflective and the other partially reflective
the photons could bounce back and forth across the crystal
knocking out photons from the
chromium atoms in synchronized waves
those ordered waves escaped through
the partial reflective side
appearing to us as a laser beam
the first laser only produced short pulses of a few Watts
like igniting a bonfire to get a candle's worth of light
but it was still an unprecedented capability
a Nobel prize winning one in fact
early designs struggled to pump in large amounts
of energy or get it back out as a laser beam
without incurring huge efficiency losses
engineers rapidly got to expanding their
capabilities and improving their efficiency
different types of lasers were tested
ranging from fluorescent dyes under concentrated sunlight
to driving shock waves down gas tubes using high explosives
even radiation from a nuclear reactor was
investigated as a source of laser pumping energy
they all failed by being too impractical
dangerous or expensive
what did succeed was fiber lasers and semiconductor lasers
fiber lasers take a source of light and send it down
an optical fiber made of a special glass which has
atoms of ytterbium or neodymium embedded inside
the length of the fiber gives those atoms plenty
of chances to absorb the light energy and release
it as a narrow high quality laser beam
semiconductor lasers are somewhat
like solar cells in reverse
instead of using layers of semiconductors like gallium
arsenide to absorb external sunlight to produce electricity
they consume electricity to release their own photons
those photons are bounced between microscopic mirror
layers so they come out as a single laser beam
semiconductor lasers are easy to
manufacture and tune to specific needs
making them very popular
fiber and semiconductor lasers only need electricity to run
operate at reasonable temperatures
and can be scaled from microchips to the size of buildings
they're also exceedingly versatile
especially when frequency doubling is used
it's a technique where a laser beam passes
through a special non linear crystal
which contains structures that can capture two photons
and convert them into one higher energy photon
this is why lasers are used everywhere from playing with
your cat and scanning barcodes to cutting steel to
delivering this video to you through fiber internet
connections
the world's militaries have also picked up
on the potential of laser technology
they are used as laser gyroscopes
to guide submarines underwater
or as communication devices to
securely transmit information
lasers are also used to attack by guiding bombs or
triggering proximity fuses for air to air missiles
or defend against those same missiles by shining
a beam on the missile's sensors to blind it
but what about laser weapons
where are they as this technology becomes commonplace
the first problem to solve is producing a spot
small enough and powerful enough at distance
the size of the spot at a certain distance
is determined by the laser wavelength
the beam quality and the diameter of
the weapon's focusing mirror
lenses can also focus laser beams
but they are much heavier and harder
to manufacture than a mirror
so all serious designs use wide mirrors
Beam power matters a lot too
divide the Beam power by the spot area
and you get an intensity in Watts per square centimeter
a realistic green laser focused by a ten centimeter diameter
mirror can create a spot about ten centimeters wide at ten
kilometers with an area of seventy eight square centimeters
with a one meter wide mirror
it can produce the same spot at a
distance of a hundred kilometers
ten kilowatts divided by this area nets us one
hundred and twenty eight Watts per square centimeter
which is enough to start melting most metals
no aircraft can be made shiny enough to avoid this damage
an effective weapon however must do more
than just slowly erode a target surface
it must blast through it
delivering a destructive amount of
energy in a short amount of time
that's why the laser intensity should be
compared to the target's hardness
given in jewels per square centimeter
the hardness of different targets can only
really be estimated by real world testing
but we know we need about a kilojoule per
square centimeter to destroy a drone
and a missile or aircraft takes tens of
kilowatts per square centimeter
an icbm warhead protected by its reentry heat shield cone
has a hardness on the order of hundreds of kilojoules
equivalent to setting off eight sticks of dynamite
on every palm sized patch the laser touches
a ten kilowatt beam however would take nearly
eight seconds to overcome the hardness of a drone
or a minute and a half to damage a missile
clearly that's not enough
the intensity must be greatly increased
doubling the focusing mirror's diameter
quadruples the intensity of its spot
but mirror sizes quickly become impractical
reducing the wavelength generally isn't an option
that leaves raising the laser power
the accepted thresholds are ten
kilowatts for handling drones
a hundred kilowatts for defeating missiles at short range
and climbing to megawatts for taking on
fighter jets or tougher targets
militarys have been trying to reach
these thresholds for decades
why is it so hard to create a powerful laser
beam and deliver it across many kilometers
several technologies have been pursued for untold
millions of dollars with successful megawatt lasers
being produced only to be discarded for their drawbacks
chemical fuel lasers were an exciting early option
like the co laser used inside the yal-1 airborne
laser testbed that flew aboard this boeing seven
four seven generating megawatt beams focused by a
rotating one point five meter diameter mirror
the coil or chemical oxygen iodine
laser worked by combining chlorine  iodine
hydrogen peroxide
and potassium hydroxide to get a hot gas
then passed that gas through a nozzle like a rocket engine
in that nozzle
iodide ions would form
ready to release their excess energy as photons
mirrors lining the nozzle walls would gather and
direct those photons out as a laser beam
rocket engines easily reach gigawatts of output
so converting just a fraction of their power as a
laser beam was enough to produce a powerful weapon  however
testing proved the technology impractical
the fuels were toxic and prone to exploding
the exhaust hot and corrosive
and the plane could only carry
enough fuel for twenty shots
it was a technological dead end
another example is the carbon dioxide laser
it's another sort of gas laser where a hot gas is
heated and passed through a mirror lined nozzle
this time the gas is carbon dioxide
which is relatively safe
and the heating can be done by
burning regular kerosene and air
it's a simple
reliable technology that is still used
today to produce powerful laser cutters
but they use electrical heating today
during the cold war the Soviets even tried to
launch a satellite into orbit equipped with
a one megawatt carbon dioxide laser
their mistake was using a soviet rocket to do it
it flipped on its way up and crashed
they are especially popular with biomedical applications
as the beam they produce is heavily absorbed by water
which means the laser can be absorbed quickly as
heat and not penetrate deeper into the tissue
perfect for precise medical procedures
but it's twenty times harder to focus
than a green wavelength laser
so it's only useful at short ranges
it's modern semiconductor and fiber laser technology that
has restored the hope for a practical laser weapon
individually these lasers are weak
capable of only a hundred to a thousand
Watts before melting from internal heat
beam combining is the trick that allows them to
climb to higher powers by merging dozens of
individual lasers into a single giant beam
the most advanced modern weapons actually use
semiconductor lasers to generate the raw power they need
then send it through fiber lasers to
turn it into many high quality beams
which are merged for an output in
the hundreds of kilowatts
this technology is being deployed right now in rafale's
one hundred kilowatt iron beam or aboard the u s Navy's
one hundred and fifty kilowatt Helios laser
Lockheed Martin is pushing its high energy laser from
three hundred kilowatts to five hundred kilowatts too
these modern lasers also get good efficiency
with thirty to fifty percent of the electricity they
consume reaching the focusing mirror as light
and they are pretty compact
it may not be long before jet fighters are carrying one
hundred kilowatt pods on their usual hard points
or air defense battalions are equipped with trucks with a
one megawatt laser turret instead of a missile launcher
power is however useless if it can't reach the target
the second major challenge preventing laser
weapons is getting through the atmosphere
a Beam is expected to travel through air filled
with dust or clouds that scatter the light
atmosphere gases absorb whole sections
of the electromagnetic spectrum
water vapor
for example
completely blocks the mid infrared
beams of a carbon dioxide laser
the air itself also acts like a moving lens that
distorts or bends the beam traversing it
a rough rule of thumb is that if the
image of a target can't reach you
then your laser beam can't reach it either
the distortions that make stars twinkle mirages appear or
mountains disappear into blue haze also affect laser beams
researchers have spent years investigating each
phenomenon and devising ways to avoid or negate them
restricting laser wavelengths from blue to red
plus a small number of infrared bands
gets past most atmospheric absorption
Adaptive Optics try to undo distortions that bend
light's path through air by measuring them
then reversing them with a flexible mirror
getting through fog
dust or clouds is much harder
1 the brute force method is to carve a channel through
them by simply vaporizing anything in the Beam's path
this requires an enormous amount of power
rising to hundreds of megawatts if the
target is sitting inside a thunderstorm
so new techniques are being developed to create
a channel using more efficient mechanisms
such as shattering water droplets with short laser pulses
or sweeping particles out of the way using shock waves
that may only cost a few kilowatts
what is certain however is that the cost
of laser weapons is falling rapidly
cold war era programs cost billions
with the yal one reaching eleven
billion for a single plane
in a twenty twenty four us Naval
institute's congressional report
it stated that a sixty kilowatt laser
weapon would cost one hundred million
while a two hundred and fifty kilowatt
version would cost two hundred million
it sounds like a lot
but it means that an effective laser is already inside the
cost bracket of an existing gun or missile based system
while retaining the benefit of only
needing a few dollars a minute to run
commercially available lasers are doubling in power
while also falling in cost every five years
and these improvements are likely to
carry over to military lasers
by the end of this decade
we can expect to see megawatt lasers cost
no more than a few million dollars
about the price of a main battle
tank or older jet fighter plane
many Nations would be able to afford them
so they'd be deployed in large numbers around the world
what could they do then
and how would this transform warfare
by the end of the decade
we may have mobile one Megawatt green
lasers like this roaming the battlefield
as an air defense weapon
it can be extraordinary
it can shoot through thousands of
drones or hundreds of missiles
militaries would have to adapt by sending in
their attacks as low as possible to the ground
so that they'll only be exposed to the
laser at the last possible moment
this restricts their offensive range and forces
them to be sent in less frequent mass attacks
aircraft would have a much harder
time when lasers are in the area
flying low consumes more fuel and reduces payload
stealth could be used to come closer to
the laser before it starts firing
but any error would result in instant fireballs
avoiding that means relying on much more advanced
aircraft equipped with standoff munitions
both of which would cost a lot more
on the other hand
large planes could mount massive lasers that
would flip the table on ground defense
instead of the lumbering targets for
long range missiles they are today
they'd become gunships surrounded by a
megawatt exclusion zone that keeps out
missiles and any plane with a smaller laser
a satellite at a four hundred kilometer altitude
the same height as the iss
would not survive more than four
seconds against a megawatt laser
just one beam could clean out orbital bands over time
potentially entire low orbit constellations
for the cost of a few dollars
Battlefield intelligence becomes restricted
making air attacks even less coordinated
and easier for the laser to defeat
the effects are compounding everywhere
and they hurt western militaries the most
they are the ones that aim for air dominance
and expect to use their large number of non stealthy
aircraft to wipe out ground forces once they achieve it
lasers are an inexhaustible counter to that strategy
lasers have an effect at a grander scale too
ballistic missiles are terrifying because
they are very expensive to defend against
so few sites are protected
nuclear warheads come screaming down at extreme velocities
slamming into the ground fifteen to thirty
seconds after touching the atmosphere
a single megawatt laser turret could only
defeat a handful of them in that time
it's not a perfect defense
but it might be something many
nations could afford to set up
a large nuclear power would happily
sacrifice a few warheads to punch through
a small power might only have a few
warheads available in total
1 but none of this means that drones  missiles
aircraft or ballistic missiles become obsolete  2
older planes with bombs get replaced by
a smaller number of stealthy jets
cruise missiles that efficiently travel at high
altitude are reused for short range strikes
satellites are sent on inclined orbits to catch
glimpses of the battlefield from the sides
more warheads have to be loaded
onto each ballistic missile
which makes maintaining nuclear arsenals a greater burden
ground forces are the big winners
tanks can be used more aggressively
when the Aerial threat is reduced
Megawatt lasers can skewer light
vehicles like armored personnel carriers
but they are not more or less effective in
that role than a regular auto cannon
and artillery will continue to be a
centerpiece of surface action
so countries with large
conventional forces get a relative boost  at sea
vessels of all types would be better defended by lasers
it would serve as an inexhaustible defense that would
require an overwhelming volley of missiles to overcome
concentrating firepower and therefore grouping ships
into large fleets instead of scattering them across
the ocean would be necessary to win engagements
that's an important consequence for the us trying to
cover both the Atlantic and the Pacific while China
is trying to pry open gaps in its defense
despite all this
it's the west that's likely to first adopt laser weapons
and be the first to devise tactics that
exploit them as much as possible
of course  we don't know what the future of
warfare will actually look like
technologies can be theorycrafted for years
only to be used in completely
unexpected ways on the real battlefield
what we do know is that the problems holding back
laser weapon technology will soon be solved
and when that happens
great changes must be expected
only time will tell how significant they'll be
progress in technology often comes down to the
tools engineers have at their disposal
and onshape is one of my favorite tools
i currently have at my disposal
onshape is a professional grade CAD and PDM
system built entirely on the cloud
that means no downloads
no installs
and no hardware limitations
it runs directly in your browser
because of that
you can design from anywhere on nearly any device
even a phone or tablet
and it's free to try for six months to all
engineers and companies by going to onshape
pro slash realengineering
i honestly love this software
being able to just type the onshape url into
a browser and instantly access my files
create new files or view old ones is incredibly handy
last week  i wanted to mount my Hurley to the wall
where it will sit until i get the once in a year
call up as emergency cover on a sub's bench  so
i typed onshape into my browser
created a shape after measuring the Hurley
and had it printing next to me five minutes later
i no longer work as a real engineer
but if i did
i could see myself pulling my phone out during
technical sales meetings to show a customer a detail
or quickly using my phone as a second screen to
check dimensions as i design on my computer
browser based systems just have a ton of
flexibility in how you use them
it also makes collaboration seamless
you can share and work in others in real time
just like in Google docs
every single action is automatically recorded
so you can roll back to earlier
versions whenever you need to
this would have been the dream for
group college projects too
onshape even borrows ideas from git hub
allowing you to branch and merge designs
if someone wants to explore a new idea
they can now do so in their own branch
without affecting the main project
and merge it back in later if it works
that's a really powerful tool for innovative companies
it empowers designers to explore
new ideas in a low risk way
the result is that everyone on your team always has
access to a single up to date source of truth
no more lost files or version confusion
onshape is now offering engineers and their companies
up to six months free of the professional version
if you're an engineer or a product designer
i highly recommend checking it out
you can get started for free at onshape  com
Ford slash realengineering